Celebrate people's history.
Reparations now, reparations won.
From 1972 to 1991, a former Chicago police commander, John
Birch and his men systematically tortured over 119 African
American men and women.
Following decades of struggle by groups such as black people
against police torture in 2013, the Chicago torture justice
memorials introduced a reparations ordinance in City Hall
demanding holistic reparations for torture survivors and their
families.
With pressure from grassroots organizing on May 6, 2015,
Chicago became the first US municipality to provide
reparations for racially motivated police violence.
The additional fifth star on the Chicago flag represents the
devastating impact that torture has had on survivors and
their communities.
So for this piece, I was thinking about all the different
people who led the fight for reparations and what really struck
me the most was the mothers of survivors who fought for
reparations for their for their sons.
So here in the forefront is Mary L Johnson, who was the mother
of a birch torture survivor.
Who is the mother of a birch torture survivor and she really
let the fight she filed the lawsuit.
She was like was fighting so hard and people joined her and
lawyers joined her and I really wanted to make sure that
mothers were not left out of this of this history because I
think a lot of I think a lot of mainstream news will focus
on the lawyers and will focus on the attorneys, but I think
and of course they're critical right, but I think that the
mother is really where the foundation and the backbone for
this fight.
And then in the background, you know, this is part of a photo
image that's much larger and longer of just like dozens of
people who are holding these banners, these black banners, with
the names of people who are tortured by birch and his and
his, you know, his crew.
And then it has at the bottom the, you know, tortured in Chicago
on this date.
And there was just like dozens and dozens and dozens of
people holding these banners like arm to arm.
And I really love that image and wanted to make sure that
that that image was integrated into this piece.
And yeah, and the fact you asked me about colors in the last
piece, I really love blues.
I think blues like I just I'm a fan of blues and so I tend
to go towards more blue hues when I make my pieces.
And I, yeah, so for this one I went with blue.
I wanted to make sure that the Chicago flag was also
front and center because this is a Chicago torture justice
Memorial t-shirt where they added a fifth star to the flag
that represented all of the torture survivors.
Yeah, yeah, I really love this piece to it.
It was it was difficult in terms of medium because I I did paint
it, but then once it was uploaded and then had to get off
and printed the colors change a little bit so they got a little
bit deeper than the original piece did.
So that was a little hard to like let that go.
But, but I think it still works and it's still really powerful.
But this piece was yeah, so so fun to make.
I made it in 2020.
Josh McFee had reached out and had asked if I wanted to contribute
a piece in front based on movement history in Chicago and
I was like, of course, yeah, here's like a laundry list of things
I would love to cover and we wanted to focus more on something
that's a win so that we had like a sort of nice story arc
to share in this piece.
So we went with the reparations fight.
And I really in this and it was so hard to write that little paragraph
of text because there's so much you can, you know, like I could have
talked about we charge genocide for like an hour and I was like,
I need to cut it short.
And then this one I could talk about for a whole hour too,
just like thinking about all of the different people who kicked
off this effort, right?
And all of the different artists and lawyers and attorneys and
cultural workers and young people and community activists who
threw down to make this happen.
And I think that the reparations, the five reparations is a great
example of when you have everybody on board because everybody
understands that our struggles are intertwined, right?
And so like, and we all have different skill sets that really
just can create such a comprehensive, incredible,
the strategic campaign.
And so that I think of that with reparations, I think of that
with no copycatomy, which I'm sure we'll talk about later.
One more thing I want to add about this because I think it relates
to the power of art is this reparation package was so comprehensive, right?
It included like financial compensation for survivors in their,
and their families included tuition for survivors in their,
and their children and families, it per, you know, mental health space.
They have the Chicago torture just a center now, right?
For mental health and wellness, they included teaching the
community, and they had a lot of work to do with the public
and the community.
And so that was a great example of how the public is experiencing
the pandemic and the pandemic and the community has a very different
approach towards your history in eighth and tenth grade and Chicago
public schools.
So many other things.
And it also included a public memorial.
Well, all of the other things happened.
Except for the memorial right away.
And, you know,
I just wasn't happening.
And I think that that is intentional.
It is completely intentional because what more powerful would be,
like, what more powerful, what, you know, then a public memorial in,
like an infrastructure that sits on the south side that tells the story to
everyday people, not just people like that are in organizing community
and adjacent who know this history, right?
But like everyday people walking by to see that this torture happened.
And that people were given reparations for it.
Like how much more empowering could that be, right?
And for that to be the last thing that was prioritized by the city,
I think is very telling of the power of art.
100%.
It's really cool that you brought this piece up because we just celebrated
last night that final piece.
Chicago torture just says memorial had a had a celebration.
It is the one that was brought up by the city,
this one,
which was the one that was involved in.
In some way, which so many people were.
And we,
yes,
celebrated the full funding of the public memorial,
which was the last piece of the package.
It's like,
it makes you think about what's beyond what's in front of us, right?
Because I think what the public mainstream.
Media shares is that,
oh,
there's a police shooting?
I mean,
So is this cop going to go to jail or face charges?
It's like, we don't have to just go that direction.
We can go the direction of how about just financially,
like a public or formal apology from the city financially,
supporting not just these survivors,
but like the generations to come after them.
How about we move towards that as like,
you know, and that it's possible.
It's not impossible, right?
Should we just did it?
And so I think that yeah,
so just like, at going what you're saying,
that it just makes a stink of be way beyond what's in front of us
and what's possible.